Guide to the David Hamburg papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IX: United Nations
  The series contains meeting minutes, correspondence, research materials and subject files documenting Hamburg’s work in international organizations on a variety of health, behavior, education and conflict resolution subjects. The agencies include UNESCO, several World Health Organization Committees (Advisory Committee on Medical Research, Pan American Committee on Health Research Policies, Research and Training in Tropical Diseases), and Office of the UN High Commissioner on Refugees, including Refugee Education Trust project. For additional information see also Institutonal Correspondence (Sereis III.2) for these institutions, particularly ms. boxes 386-388.
  - UNESCO, UNICEF, WHO, 1971-1982 (Box 720)
  - WHO, 1981-1982 (Box 721)
  - WHO, 1981-1982 (Box 722)
  - Various agencies, 1983-1996 (Box 723)
  - Various agencies, 1997-2002 (Box 724)
  - UNHCR -Refugee Education Trust project, 1998-2003 (Box 826)
  - UNHCR -Refugee Education Trust project, 1998-2002 (Box 725)
  - Various agencies, 1998-2002 (Box 827)
  - Background Materials, 1975-2000 (Box 726)
- Series X: Writings and Speeches
  Series contains Dr. Hamburg's remarks, speeches, articles, and books, CVs, Lists of Publications and presentations, reprints, and related materials. Since Hamburg tended to consult and reuse his previous works on later occasions, many older writings are grouped together with newer works that are based on them, and, occasionally, with other background materials. Many articles are undated and/or fragmentary. Some of Hamburg's writings are found in Alpha Files when associated with a person or institution, or under specific project/subject area, or in the institution-based series of the years corresponding to this period.
  - Subseries X.1: Education for Conflict Resolution (ECR) Books
    The series contains Chapter drafts, research material and related correspondence for Hamburg's two books on conflict resolution: Learning to Live Together and No More Killing Fields (sometimes called “Book I” and “Book II” or by its draft title Earth is Not Flat ); Closely related to PDC materials in series I.7 and other conflict resolution writings during Hamburg’s tenure as the Carnegie Corporation president. The series contains some speeches, presentations, etc. given based on book drafts.
    - Writings and Background Materials, 1974-1990 (Box 727)
    - Writings and Background Materials, 1991-1993 (Box 728)
    - Writings and Background Materials on U.N., Civil Society, Ethnic Conflict, 1993-2000 (Box 729)
    - Writings and Background Materials, January 1993-August 1993 (Box 730)
    - Writings and Background Materials, August 1993-September 1993 (Box 731)
    - Writings and Background Materials, September 1993-1995 (Box 732)
    - Writings and Background Materials, 1996-1997 (Box 733)
    - Writings and Background Materials, WWII chapters, 1997-1999 (Box 734)
    - Writings and Background Materials, 1998-November 1998 (Box 735)
    - Writings and Background Materials, December 1998-May 1999 (Box 736)
    - Writings and Background Materials, June 1999-August 1999 (Box 737)
    - Writings and Background Materials, September 1999-October 1999 (Box 738)
    - Writings and Background Materials, November 1999-December 1999 (Box 739)
    - Writings and Background Materials - Democracy and Development, 1982-1999 (Box 740)
    - Writings and Background Materials - No More Killing fields, 1982-1999 (Box 825)
    - Writings and Background Materials, 2000-February 2000 (Box 741)
    - Writings and Background Materials, February 2000-April 2000 (Box 742)
    - Writings and Background Materials, May 2000-June 2000 (Box 743)
    - Writings and Background Materials, July 2000-July 2000 (Box 744)
    - Writings and Background Materials, August 2000-September 2000 (Box 745)
    - Writings and Background Materials, September 2000-October 2000 (Box 746)
    - Writings and Background Materials, October 2000-November 2000 (Box 747)
    - Writings and Background Materials, November 2000-January 2001 (Box 748)
    - Writings and Background Materials, January 2001-April 2001 (Box 749)
    - Writings and Background Materials, April 2001-June 2001 (Box 750)
    - Writings and Background Materials, July 2001-August 2001 (Box 751)
    - Writings and Background Materials, September 2001-December 2001 (Box 752)
    - Writings and Background Materials, December 2001-February 2002 (Box 753)
    - Writings and Background Materials, March 2002-May 2002 (Box 754)
    - Writings and Background Materials, June 2002-December 2002 (Box 755)
    - Writings and Background Materials, 2003- (Box 756)
    - Writings and Background Materials, 2003- (Box 757)
  - Subseries X.2: Children and Youth
    The series consists of materials assembled in the course of working on the book Today's Children, predominantly notes, marked-up copies of Hamburg’s earlier writings, chapter drafts, correspondence related to publication and distribution of the book.
    - Today's Children chapters and preceding writings, 1980-1994 (Box 758)
    - Today's Children chapters and preceding writings, 1980-1994 (Box 759)
    - Today's Children chapters and preceding writings, 1980-1994 (Box 760)
    - Summaries and ads for Today's Children, 1991-1994 (Box 761)
    - Distribution and Presentations of Today's Children, 1991-1994 (Box 762)
    - Reviews and paperback edition, 1991-1994 (Box 763)
    - Responses and quotes for Today's Children, 1991-1994 (Box 764)
  - Subseries X.3: General
    Extensive collection of published and unpublished essays, speeches, lectures, magazine articles, reports, and research papers by David Hamburg, including many fragmentary or undated items. Arranged in loose chronological order, except for the cases when a set of writings on related subjects was deliberately kept together by Hamburg. Also includes Hamburg’s cumulative lists of works and presentations, and his CVs over the years.
    - Cumulative lists of works, CVs, early writings, 1949-1981 (Box 765)
    - Chapter for "Great Apes" books, early writings, 1953-1981 (Box 766)
    - Writings and speeches, 1961-1978 (Box 767)
    - Writings and speeches, 1961-1984 (Box 768)
    - Writings and speeches, 1975-1988 (Box 769)
    - Hamburg-Sartorius monograph", 1982-1986 (Box 770)
    - Aggression and Conflict, 1973-1986 (Box 771)
    - Writings and speeches, 1977-1986 (Box 772)
    - Health, behavior and policy, 1978-1991 (Box 773)
    - Writings and speeches, 1979-1987 (Box 774)
    - Writings and speeches, 1983-1997 (Box 775)
    - Writings and speeches, 1998-2003 (Box 776)
    - Undated writings and speeches (Box 777)
    - Printed monographs, written or edited by Hamburg, 1970-1997 (Box 778)
- Series XI: Biographical Files
  This series contains various materials relating to dr. Hamburg’s life and work, but not specifically pertaining to any given project or organization.
  - Subseries XI.1: Personal
    Series consists of calendars, notebooks, documents, cumulative lists of works, personal correspondence, and materials relating to professional activities of David Hamburg’s wife and two children. Also includes a box of personal correspondence related to his Carnegie Corporation presidency.
    - Notes, more notes (Box Box)
    - Documents and correspondence, 1949-1982 (Box 779)
    - Correspondence re: Carnegie Corporation presidency, 1982- (Box 780)
    - Documents and correspondence, 1983-1997 (Box 781)
    - DAH appointment calendars, 1976-1983 (Box 782)
    - DAH appointment calendars, 1983-1990 (Box 783)
    - DAH appointment calendars, 1991-1997 (Box 784)
    - DAH appointment calendars and correspondence, 1997-1999 (Box 785)
    - Beatrix "Betty" McCleary Hamburg, wife, 1960-1999 (Box 786)
    - Children, Margaret "Peggy" Hamburg and Eric Hamburg, 1960-1999 (Box 787)
    - Cumulative contact files and lists, 1988-2001 (Box 788)
  - Subseries X.2: Emeritus
    This series consists of the files, representing mix of personal and professional and activities after retiring from active role at the Carnegie Corporation. The materials include correspondence, transcript of Oral History interview, autobiographical notes, typescript of memoirs, invitations and materials relating to various conferences, receptions and awards, Hamburg’s participation and support of numerous projects on public health and conflict prevention.
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2000 (Box 789)
    - Correspondence and events, 1999-2000 (Box 790)
    - Correspondence and events, 2000-2001 (Box 791)
    - Vital Voices project, 2000-2001 (Box 792)
    - Correspondence and events, 2000-2002 (Box 793)
    - Oral History, 1999-2003 (Box 794)
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 828)
    - Prevention of Teen Pregnancy project, 1998-2003 (Box 829)
    - Correspondence and events: International Peace Academy, International Centre for Transitional Justice, Monterey Institute of International Studies, 1998-2003 (Box 830)
    - Correspondence and events; "I Am Your Child" video series, 1998-2003 (Box 831)
    - Correspondence and events; New York Academy of Medicine, Pritzker Research Fund, 1998-2003 (Box 832)
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 833)
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 834)
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 835)
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 836)
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 837)
    - Typescript of Hamburg's memoirs, 1998-2003 (Box 838)
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 839)
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 840)
    - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 841)
- Series XII: Background Research Materials
  Subject files of clippings and printed materials All subseries with "Background" in the title contain outside published materials (books, newspaper clippings, magazine articles, reports etc.); and 3rd party unpublished writings (conference papers; other writings not clearly directly done for CCNY) related to whatever series they are connected to. Most large series have their own "background" subseries, though in some "background" is included-- this will be noted in the contents description. Some "background" materials that are included in folders with other memos, notes, etc. will appear in the main series. Some material in "background" series include marginal reading notes or very brief coverletters.
  - General health, 1970-1999 (Box 795)
  - Children and families, 1970-1980 (Box 796)
  - Weapons of mass destruction, 1975-1995 (Box 797)
  - Health general, 1977-1999 (Box 798)
  - Health policy and behavior, 1977-1995 (Box 799)
  - HIV/AIDS, 1987-1998 (Box 800)
  - Health and behavior, 1980-1997 (Box 801)
  - Health general, 1980-1997 (Box 802)
  - Preventing Deadly Conflict -- Aggression, 1980-1990 (Box 803)
  - Miscellanious notes and clippings, 1980-1999 (Box 804)
  - Miscellanious notes and clippings, 1991-1999 (Box 805)
  - Miscellanious notes and clippings, 1997-2000 (Box 806)
- Series XIII: Audiovisual Materials
  This small series, described on folder and item level, consists of photographs, slide and transparencies, audio, video, and digital materials from David Hamburg collection. Audio and video materials primarily represent conference presentations and addresses, many of them were digitized for preservation and access purposes, including reel-to-reel audio tapes of a Hamburg-Goodall presentation during the Burg Wartenstein Conference #62 "The Behavior of Great Apes" organized by David Hamburg and Jane Goodall in August of 1974.
  - Recording by/of D. Hamburg and J. Goodall at Burg Warstein Symposium #62: The Behavior of Great Apes, 1974 July (Box 440)
    Formerly 10 Reel-to-Reel Audio Tapes, 1/4”, separated from Series IV.1 box 440, and digitized, available as 20 mp3 files upon request.
  - Potential Material for WPII”, nd (Box 128)
    Formerly on Audio Cassette. Separated from Series I.7.A Box 128 and digitized, available as mp3 file upon request.
  - Voice of America Africa Division Program Sampler, 1994-10-01T00:00:00 (Box 42)
    Formerly on Audio Cassette. Separated from Series III.2, Box 42 and digitized, available as mp3 file upon request.
  - Recordings of Preventing Deadly Conflict Meetings, February-January 1993 (Box electronic)
    Formerly 7 Micro Dictating Audio Cassettes, digitized, available as 8 mp3 files upon request.
  - Undated photos of Beatrix and David Hamburg (Box 807)
  - Stanford Primate Research program - chimpanzee photos with letter to Jane Goodall, 1972 (Box 807)
    15 b&w prints, 8x10
  - Photo of Members of Carnegie Task Force on Meeting the Needs of Young Children, 1994-04-01T00:00:00 (Box 807)
    Color print, 5” x 7”. Separated from Series I.6, Box 87
  - Photographs of David Hamburg and Al Gore from PCAST Meeting, 1995-03-01T00:00:00 (Box 807)
    2 color 8x10 prints, Separated from Series II.1, box 207
  - Photographs from The Culture of Peace Program in Jordan, [circa May 1998-1999] (Box 807)
    7 color prints, 4” x 6”, Separated from Series I.7.B., box 142
  - Stanford Biology Presentation Slides, 1965 (Box 807)
  - Slides for Preventing Deadly Conflict overview presentation, [circa 1996-1997] (Box 807)
    8 slides separated from Series I.7.A., Box 112
  - Disk labeled “Int. Foundation” related to projects with E. Velikhov, [ca. 1988-1989] (Box 807)
    5 1/4” Floppy Disk, Separated from Series I.8.C
  - Disk labeled, “Global Warming Impacts and Solutions”, [ca. 1990-1991] (Box 807)
    3.5” Floppy Disk, Separated from Series I.8.C
  - Research for Better Schools, Thinking and Rural At-Risk Student, produced by PBS, 28 Min., 1990 (Box 807)
    VHS Videotape, Separated from Series I.6 Box 92
  - Northwestern University Annenberg Washington Program of Communication Studies, Electronic Library of Program Publications, 1983-1996 (Box 807)
    CD
  - Cassette titled, White House Conference on Teenagers, May 2, 2000, with Hilary Clinton, 2000 May (Box 807)
    VHS, Separated from Series I.6, Box 87
- Series XIV: Realia
  Medals, plaques and framed award certificates given to David Hamburg by various organizations over the course of his career.
  - Awards and plaques (Box 808)
    Oversized
  - Awards and plaques (Box 809)
  - Awards and plaques (Box 810)
  - Awards and plaques, blueprints of Stanford Primate Facility (IV.2) (Box 811)
  - Awards, plaques, medals (Box 812)
  - Plaques, awards, medals (Box 813)